# Mohammad Rafay Aleem

mrafayaleem@gmail.com

+971558468033

LinkedIn: <u>linkedin.com/in/mrafayaleem</u>

# Summary

I am a highly motivated software professional who takes keen interest in software requirements gathering, design principles and software implementation.

I joined dubizzle (the leading classifieds website in the Middle East) right after graduating as a Software Engineering major, and since then, I have managed to worked on some commendable projects in a very short span of time. Some of the most fascinating things that I played around with were tools such as Apache Kafka, celery, haproxy, PostgreSQL and AWS as well as techniques such as load-balancing using nginx / haproxy and tracking down race conditions within our code base.

## Experience

## Software Engineer

dubizzle (An OLX company) - Dubai, United Arab, United Arab Emirates January 2016 - Present

#### Jr. Software Engineer

dubizzle (An OLX company) - Dubai, United Arab, United Arab Emirates June 2014 - December 2015

- Re-wrote archiving of old ads to take away the load from the main DB. Used PostgreSQL jsonb with Django to allow for arbitrary dumps on archive tables.
- Performed massive DB migrations on production DB using Percona Toolkit to avoid any downtime on the site.
- Wrote a nice Python library to generate XSD schemas based on class definitions, do validations and convert XML to Python dictionary.
- Extensively employed remote-pdb, celery-rdb and syslog to track down bugs.
- Worked on improving and optimizing our in-house image uploading service.
- Took full responsibility of maintaining and monitoring our service layer between CRM and products.
- Leveraged Apache Kafka to improve our service layer between CRM and products.
- Created load tests using Apache JMeter to trace bottlenecks in CRM and image uploading services.
- Worked on some major and minor bug fixes on UAE site.
- Wrote a new web service for vehicle number plate search using Python Bottle framework.
- Worked on migrating the site from Django 1.4 to 1.7.10.

### Software Development Intern

KTH Applied Information and Security Lab – NUST SEECS June 2013 – August 2013 (3 months)

Implemented OpenStack Swift object storage encryption using PyCrypto Python Cryptography Toolkit.

## **Chief Coordinator**

Game Development Club - NUST SEECS

April 2013 – May 2013 (2 months)

Responsible for arranging seminars, tech-talks and workshops on game development at NUST.

### Kinect Development Intern

**NUST SEECS** 

July 2012 – August 2012 (2 months)

Implemented a gesture based user interface library for Kinect device.

## Android Development Intern

Whizpoint – NUST SEECS
October 2011 – January 2012 (4 months)
Worked on Android API and SQLite.

## Qualifications

## National University of Sciences and Technology - Islamabad

Software Engineering (CGPA 3.20)

2010 - 2014

## The City School – Karachi

A Levels, Pre-Engineering, 3 A's, 1B 2008 – 2010

## Beacon Light Academy – Karachi

O Levels, Pre-Engineering, 7 A's, 2 B's

2002 – 2008

# **Projects**

## Gdx-Sqlite

Authored a cross-platform open source Libgdx extension for SQLite database handling which gathered interest from the Libgdx community. Can be viewed on: <a href="https://github.com/mrafayaleem/qdx-sqlite">https://github.com/mrafayaleem/qdx-sqlite</a>.

#### Fruit Filch for Android

June 2012 – August 2012

Designed an award winning Android game using Libgdx framework.

### EduBot Educational Search Engine

September 2011 - February 2012

A miniature search engine developed as a project for our Data Structures course.

### Moodle Plugin

December 2011 - February 2012

Developed a Moodle plugin for our Database course.

## **Honors and Awards**

2<sup>nd</sup> Position – Mobilink Jazz Jazba 'GBG' Contest Mobilink Pakistan November 2012 Awarded for Fruit Filch Android game.

Winner – Punjab Youth Festival Game Development Competition Government of Punjab, Pakistan October 2012 Awarded for Fruit Filch Android game.

Have worked with: Python, Apache Kafka, celery, Django, bottle, flask, AWS, Java, Libgdx, OpenStack Swift, Kinect API, Android API, SDN, POX, Mininet